Just to put everything in context,
فقط لوضع كل شيء في سياق محدد
and to kind of give you a background to where I'm coming from,
وحتى تأخذون فكرة من أي مكان انا قادم
so that a lot of the things I'm going to say,
هناك اشياء كثيره سأقولها.
and the things I'm going to do --
واشياء سأقوم بها
or things I'm going to tell you I've done --
أو أشياء قمت بها سأحدثكم عنها.
you will understand exactly why and how I got motivated to be where I am.
سوف تتفهمون كيف وما هي الدوافع التي اوصلتني إلى ما وصلت إليه.
I graduated high school in Cleveland, Ohio, 1975.
تخرجت من الثانويه العليا فى مدينة كليفلاند ولاية أوهايو سنة 1975.
And just like my parents did when they finished studying abroad, we went back home.
ومثلما فعل والدي عندما أنهيت دراستي في الخارج ، عدنا إلى وطننا الأم.
Finished university education, got a medical degree, 1986.
إنتهيت من تعليمي ,وتحصلت على شهادة الطب عام 1986.
And by the time I was an intern house officer,
وبمرور الوقت كنت أحد المتدربين فى وظيفة مسئول صحة.
I could barely afford to maintain my mother's 13-year-old car --
لقد كان من الصعب علي أن أقدر على تكاليف صيانة سيارة والدتي القديمة التي عمرها 13 سنه،
and I was a paid doctor.
وقد كنت أتلقى راتب طبيب.
This brings us to why a lot of us, who are professionals,
هذا يقودنا إلى السبب في الكثير منا الذين هم محترفون
are now, as they say, in diaspora.
الان ، كما يقولون بأنهم في المهجر.
Now, are we going to make that a permanent thing,
الآن ، هل نحن سنسمح بإستمرارية ذلك،
where we all get trained, and we leave, and we don't go back?
حيث أننا جميعا حصلنا على التدريب وغادرنا ، و لا نعود؟
Perhaps not, I should certainly hope not --
ربما لا ، يجب أن أتمنى أن لا يحدث ذلك --
because that is not my vision.
والسبب لأن تلك ليست رؤيتي.
All right, for good measure, that's where Nigeria is on the African map,
حسنا, لقياس جيد، هناك تقع نيجيريا في خارطة افريقيا.
and just there is the Delta region that I'm sure everybody's heard of.
وهناك منطقة الدلتا, وانا متأكد بأن جميعنا قد سمع بها.
People getting kidnapped, where the oil comes from,
يتم إختطاف الناس، وحيث يُستخرج النفط،
the oil that sometimes I think has driven us all crazy in Nigeria.
النفط الذي في بعض الأحيان كما أعتقد يحركنا كالمجانيين في نيجيريا.
But, critical poverty: this slide is from a presentation I gave
ولكن حدة الفقر ، هذه شريحة من محاضره قدمتها
not that long ago. Gapminder.org tells the story of the gap
ليس من فترة طويله. موقع Gapminder.org يروي قصة الفجوة
between Africa and the rest of the world in terms of health care.
بين افريقيا وبقية العالم فيما يتعلق بالرعاية الصحية.
Very interesting.
مثير جدا للاهتمام.
How many people do you think are on that taxi?
كم من الناس فى رأيك تعقد بانهم على سيارة الاجرة تلك؟
And believe it or not, that is a taxi in Nigeria.
صدق أو لاتصدق بأن تلك سيارة اجرة فى نيجيريا.
And the capital -- well, what used to be the capital of Nigeria -- Lagos,
والعاصمة-- إنها عاصمة نيجيريا ، لاغوس،
that's a taxi, and you have police on them.
هذه هي سيارة أجرة ، وعليها رجل الشرطة.
So, tell me, how many policemen do you think are on this taxi? And now? Three.
إذاً ، أخبروني ، كم عدد رجال الشرطة في رأيكم في هذا التاكسي؟ و الآن؟ ثلاثة.
So, when these kind of people -- and, believe me, it's not just the police
إذاً، حينما يكون هذا النوع من هؤلاء الناس--وصدقوني ليسوا فقط رجال الشرطة
that use these taxis in Lagos. We all do. I've been on one of these,
من يقومون باستخدام سيارات الأجرة هذه في لاغوس, بل كلنا ، ولقد استخدمتها شخصياً،
and I didn't have a helmet, either.
وأنا لم اكن ارتدي القبعة الواقية حتى.
And it just reminds me of the thought of what happens when one of us
وقد ذكرني بأن أتأمل ما سيحدث لأحدنا
on a taxi like this falls off, has an accident and needs a hospital.
على التاكسي لو انزلق وحصل حادث يحتاج الى المستشفى.
Believe it or not, some of us do survive.
صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا ، بعضنا ينجو منها.
Some of us do survive malaria; we do survive AIDS.
البعض منا ينجو من مرض الملاريا، و نبقى على قيد الحياة من الايدز.
And like I tell my family, and my wife reminds me every time,
وكما اقول الى اسرتي ، وكما تذكرني زوجتي طوال الوقت،
"You're risking your life, you know, every time you go to that country."
أنت تخاطر بحياتك ، كما تعلم ، في كل مرة تذهب لهذا البلد--
And she's right. Every time you go there,
وهي صادقه. في كل مره أذهب الى هناك,
you know that if you actually need critical care --
تعرفون أنكم إن أردتم رعاية طارئة --
critical care of any sort -- if you have an accident --
رعاية طارئة من أي نوع -- إذا تعرضت لحادث،
of which there are many, there are accidents everywhere --
التي يوجد منها الكثير ، وهناك حوادث في كل مكان ،
where do they go?
إلى أين يذهبون؟
Where do they go when they need help for this kind of stuff?
أين يذهبون حينما ما يحتاجون الى مساعده من هذا القبيل؟
I'm not saying instead of, I'm saying as well as,
أنا لا أقول بدلاً من، أنا أقول كذلك أيضاً.
AIDS, TB, malaria, typhoid -- the list goes on.
الإيدز، السُل، الملاريا، التايفود -- وتستمر القائمة.
I'm saying, where do they go when they're like me?
أقول، إلى أين يذهبون عندما يكونوا من أمثالي؟
When I go back home -- and I do all kinds of things,
عندما أرجع إلى الوطن -- وأقوم بكل الأشياء،
I teach, I train -- but I catch one of these things,
أقوم بالتدريس، التدريب، لكني أُصاب بأحد هذه الأمراض،
or I'm chronically ill with one of those, where do they go?
أو إذا أصبت بمرض مزمن، إلى أين يذهبون؟
What's the economic impact when one of them dies or becomes disabled?
ما هو التأثير الإقتصادي عندما يموت أحدهم أو يصبح عاجزاً عن العمل؟
I think it's quite significant. This is where they go.
أعتقد أنه مهم جداً. إلى هنا يذهبون.
These are not old pictures and these are not from some downtrodden --
هذه ليست صوراً قديمة وهذه ليست لبعض المضطهدين--
this is a major hospital. In fact, it's from a major teaching hospital in Nigeria.
هذه مستشفى كبيرة. في الواقع، إنها من أكبر المستشفيات التعليمية في نيجيريا.
Now that is less than a year old, in an operating room.
ذلك قبل أقل من سنة مضت، في غرفة العمليات.
That's sterilizing equipment in Nigeria.
تلك هي معدات التعقيم في نيجيريا.
You remember all that oil?
هل تذكرون كل ذلك النفط؟
Yes, I'm sorry if it upsets some of you, but
نعم، أنا آسف لإغضابكم، لكن
I think you need to see this. That's the floor, OK?
أظن أنكم بحاجة لرؤية هذا. تلك هي الأرضية، حسناً؟
You can say some of this is education.
يمكنكم القول أن بعضاً من هذا هو التعليم.
You can say it's hygiene. I'm not pleading poverty.
يمكنكم القول أنها النظافة. أنا لا أتوسل فقرا.
I'm saying we need more than just, you know, vaccination,
أقول أننا بحاجة لأكثر من مجرد الأدوية،
malaria, AIDS, because I want to be treated
الملاريا، الإيدز، لأنني أريد أن أُعالج
in a proper hospital if something happens to me out there.
في مستشفى صحي إذا حدث لي أي شئ هناك.
In fact, when I start running around saying,
في الواقع، عندما بدأت بالفزع هناك وكنت أقول،
"Hey, boys and girls, you're cardiologists in the U.S.,
" هاى، يا شباب وشابات، أنتم أطباء قلب في الولايات المتحدة،
can you come home with me and do a mission?"
هل يمكنكم المجئ معي وأن نذهب في بعثة؟"
I want them to think, "Well there's some hope."
أريدهم منهم أن يفكروا، " حسناً هناك أمل."
Now, have a look at that. That's the anesthesiology machine.
الآن، أنظروا لذلك. تلك هي آلة التخدير.
And that's my specialty, right?
وهذا هو تخصصي، حسناً؟
Anesthesiology and critical care -- look at that bag.
التخدير والرعاية الطارئة -- أنظروا لتلك الحقيبة.
It's been taped with tape that we even stopped using in the U.K.
لقد تم تسجيله على شريط توقفنا عن إستعماله في المملكة المتحدة.
And believe me, these are current pictures.
وصدقوني، هذه هي الصور الحالية.
Now, if something like this, which has happened in the U.K.,
الآن، إذا كان شئ مثل هذا، قد حدث في المملكة المتحدة،
that's where they go. This is the intensive care unit in which I work.
يذهبون إلى هناك. هذه هي وحدة العناية المكثفة التي أعمل بها.
All right, this is a slide from a talk I gave
حسناً، هذه هي شريحة من محاضرة قدمتها
about intensive care units in Nigeria,
حول وحدات العناية المكثفة في نيجيريا،
and jokingly we refer to it as "Expensive Scare."
ونشير إليها مازحين ب" الرعب باهظ الثمن."
Because it's scary and it's expensive, but we need to have it, OK?
لأنها مخيفة وباهظة التكلفة، لكننا بحاجة لها.
So, these are the problems.
إذاً، ها هي المشاكل.
There are no prizes for telling us what the problems are, are there?
لا توجد جوائز لاخبارنا ما هي المشاكل، هل هناك جوائز؟
I think we all know. And several speakers before
أعتقد أن جميعنا يعرف، وعدة متحدثين من قبلي
and speakers after me are going to tell us even more problems.
ومتحدثين من بعدي سيخبرونا عن مشاكل أكثر.
These are a few of them. So, what did I do?
ها هي بعض منها. إذاً، ماذا فعلت أنا؟
There we go -- we're going on a mission.
لنمضي -- سنذهب في بعثة .
We're going to do some open-heart surgery. I was the only Brit,
سنقوم باجراء عملية قلب مفتوح، لقد كنت البريطاني الوحيد،
on a team of about nine American cardiac surgeons,
وفريق من تسعة جراحي قلب أمريكيين،
cardiac nurse, intensive care nurse.
ممرضة قلب، وممرضة عناية مكثفة.
We all went out and did a mission and we've done three of them so far.
مضينا جميعاً وقمنا ببعثة وقمنا بثلاثة منها على الأقل.
Just so you know, I do believe in missions, I do believe in aid
فقط لتعلموا، أنني أؤمن بالبعثات، وأؤمن بالمساعدات
and I do believe in charity. They have their place,
وأؤمن بالعمل الخيري. لديهم مواضعهم،
but where do they go for those things we talked about earlier?
لكن إلى اين تذهب في تلك الأشياء التي تحدثت عنها باكراً؟
Because it's not everyone that's going to benefit from a mission.
بسبب أنه لن يستفيد كل شخص من عمل البعثة.
Health is wealth, in the words of Hans Rosling.
الصحة ثروة، بكلمات هانس روزلينغ.
You get wealthier faster if you are healthy first.
أنت تصبح أكثر ثروة بسرعة إن كنت بصحة جيدة أولاً.
So, here we are, mission. Big trouble.
إذاً، ها نحن، البعثة. مشكلة كبيرة.
Open-heart surgery in Nigeria -- big trouble.
عملية قلب مفتوح في نيجيريا-- مشكلة كبيرة.
That's Mike, Mike comes out from Mississippi.
ذلك "مايك"، جاء مايك من الميسيسبي.
Does he look like he's happy?
هل يبدو فرحاً؟
It took us two days just to organize the place, but hey,
لقد أخذت منا يومين لترتيب هذا المكان.
you know, we worked on it. Does he look happy?
أتعرفون، لقد عملنا عليه. هل يبدو سعيداً؟
Yes, that's the medical advice the committee chairman says,
نعم ، ذلك هو رئيس لجنة المعدات الطبية يقول،
"Yes, I told you, you weren't going to be able to,
" نعم، لقد أخبرتكم، لن يكون بامكانكم،
you can't do this, I just know it."
لا يمكنكم فعل هذا، أنا أعرف هذا."
Look, that's the technician we had. So yes, you go on, all right?
أنظروا، ذلك هو التقني الذي لدينا. نعم، واصل أنت، حسناً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I got him to come with me -- anesthesia tech -- come with me from the U.K.
لقد جعلته يأتي معنا. تكنلوجيا التخدير، تعال معي من المملكة المتحدة.
Yes, let's just go work this thing out.
نعم، لنذهب ونفعل هذه الأشياء.
See, that's one of the problems we have in Nigeria and in Africa generally.
أنظروا، تلك هي أحد المشاكل في نيجيريا وأفريقيا عامة.
We get a lot of donated equipment.
نحصل على الكثير من المعدات كتبرع.
Equipment that's obsolete, equipment that doesn't quite work,
معدات عفا عليها الزمن، معدات لا تعمل،
or it works and you can't fix it. And there's nothing wrong with that,
أو أنها تعمل ولا يمكنك إصلاحها. ولا شئ خطأ حول ذلك،
so long as we use it and we move on.
طالما أننا نستخدمها ونواصل المسير.
But we had problems with it. We had severe problems there.
لكننا واجهنا مشاكل معها. واجهنا مشاكل حادة هناك.
He had to get on the phone. This guy was always on the phone.
توجب عليه الإتصال. هذا الشخص كان دائماً على الهاتف.
So what we going to do now?
إذاً ماذا علينا أن نفعل الآن؟
It looks like all these Americans are here and
يبدو أن كل هؤلاء الأمريكيين هنا و
yes, one Brit, and he's not going to do anything --
نعم، بريطاني واحد، ولن يفعل أي شئ،
he thinks he's British actually, and he's actually Nigerian,
إنه يعتقد أنه بريطاني في الواقع وهو في الأصل نيجيري،
I just thought about that.
لقد فكرت للتو حول ذلك.
We eventually got it working, is the truth,
وعادت للعمل في نهاية المطاف، هذه حقيقة،
but it was one of these. Even older than the one you saw.
لكنها كانت واحدة من تلك.أقدم حتى من تلك التي رأيناها.
The reason I have this picture here, this X-ray,
سبب وجود هذه الصورة هنا، هذه الأشعة السينية،
it's just to tell you where and how we were viewing X-rays.
فقط لأخبركم عن أين وكيف كنا نطالع الأشعة السينية.
Do you figure where that is? It was on a window.
هل عرفتم أين كان ذلك؟ لقد كانت على النافذة.
I mean, what's an X-ray viewing box? Please.
أعني، ما هي علبة رؤية الأشعة السينية؟ رجاءً.
Well, nowadays everything's on PAX anyway.
حسناً، على أي حال هذه الأيام كل شئ يأتي على باكس.
You look at your X-rays on a screen and you do stuff with them,
تنظر لأشعتك السينية على شاشة وتقوم بأشياء عليها،
you email them. But we were still using X-rays,
وترسلها عبر البريد الإلكتروني. لكننا كنا نستخدم اشعة سينية،
but we didn't even have a viewing box!
ولم يكن لدينا حتى صندوق للرؤية!
And we were doing open-heart surgery.
وكنا نقوم بعملية قلب مفتوح.
OK, I know it's not AIDS, I know it's not malaria,
حسناً، أعرف أنها ليست إيدز، أعرف أنها ليست ملاريا،
but we still need this stuff. Oh yeah, echo --
لكن مازلنا بحاجة لهذه المعدات. نعم، صدى --
this was just to get the children ready and the adults ready.
هذا لجعل الأطفال جاهزون والبالغين جاهزين.
People still believe in Voodoo. Heart disease,
ما يزال الناس يؤمنوا بالودونية -- أمراض القلب،
VSD, hole in the heart, tetralogies.
عيب الحاجز البطيني، ثقب في القلب، الرباعيات.
You still get people who believe in it and they came.
ما تزال تحتاج لأن يؤمن بها الناس ثم يأتون.
At 67 percent oxygen saturation, the normal is about 97.
عند تشبع الأوكسجين ب67%، والعادي هو حوالي 97%.
Her condition, open-heart surgery that as she required,
حالتها، تحتاج لعملية قلب مفتوح،
would have been treated when she was a child.
كان يتوجب علاجها منذ أن كانت طفلة.
We had to do these for adults. So, we did succeed and we still do.
كان يتوجب علينا فعل هذا للبالغين. لذا، لقد نجحنا ومازلنا نفعل.
We've done three. We're planning another one in July
لقد قمنا بثلاثة. ونخطط لواحدة في شهر يوليو
in the north of the country. So, we certainly still do open-heart,
في الجزء الشمالي للبلاد. إذاً فنحن بالتأكيد نقوم بعمليات القلب المفتوح،
but you can see the contrast between everything that was shipped in --
لكن يمكنكم رؤية التناقض في كل ما تم شحنه --
we ship everything, instruments. We had explosions
نحن نشحن كل شئ، الأجهزة-- حدثت لنا انفجارات
because the kit was designed and installed by people who weren't used to it.
لأن المعدات المقررة تم تجهيزها بواسطة أناس ليسوا معتادين على ذلك.
The oxygen tanks didn't quite work right.
لم تعمل اسطوانات الأوكسجين بالصورة الصحيحة.
But how many did we do the first one? 12.
لكن كم عملية قمنا بها أول مرة؟ 12
We did 12 open-heart surgical patients successfully.
لقد قمنا ب 12 عملية ناجحة لجراحة قلب مفتوح .
Here is our very first patient, out of intensive care,
هذا هو أول المرضى، خارج من العناية المكثفة،
and just watch that chair, all right?
فقط شاهدوا ذلك الكرسي، حسناً.
This is what I mean about appropriate technology.
هذا ما أعنيه بالتكلنوجيا المناسبة.
That's what he was doing, propping up the bed because the bed simply didn't work.
ذلك ما كان يفعله هو، يدعمون السرير لأن السرير ببساطة لم يعمل.
Have you seen one of those before?
هل رأيتم واحد من تلك من قبل؟
No? Yes? Doesn't matter, it worked.
لا؟ نعم؟ لا يهم، لقد نجحت.
I'm sure you've all seen or heard this before:
أنا متأكد من أنكم رأيتم أو سمعتم بهذا من قبل.
"We, the willing, have been doing so much with so little for so long --
نحن، الإرادة، كنا نقوم بالكثير مع القليل لفترة طويلة--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
-- we are now qualified to do anything with nothing."
-- نحن الآن مؤهلون لفعل أي شئ مع اي شئ.
Thank you. Sustainable Solutions -- this was my first company.
شكراً لكم. حلول مستدامة -- كانت هذه أول شركاتي،
This one's sole aim is to provide the very things that I think are missing.
وهدف هذه الأساسي والوحيد هو تقديم الأشياء المفقودة كما أعتقد.
So, we put my hand in my pocket and say, "Guys, let's just buy stuff.
إذاً نضع أيدينا على جيوبنا ونقول، " يا ناس، لنشتري المعدات."
Let's go set up a company that teaches people, educates them,
لنذهب ونؤسس شركة تقوم بتعليم الناس، تدريسهم،
gives them the tools they need to keep going."
تقدم لهم المعدات التي يحتاجونها لمواصلة المسير.
And that's a perfect example of one.
وذلك مثال رائع لأحدها.
Usually when you buy a ventilator in a hospital,
عادةً عندما ترغب في شراء مكيف هواء لمستشفى،
you buy a different one for children,
تشتري واحد مختلف للأطفال،
you buy a different one for transport. This one will do everything,
وتشتري واحد مختلف للتنقل. هذه ستقوم بكل شئ،
and it will do it at half the price and doesn't need compressed air.
وستقوم به بنصف السعر وهي لا تحتاج لهواء مضغوط.
If you're in America and you don't know about this one, we do,
إذا كنتم في أمريكا لا تعرفون عن هذا الشئ، نحن نعرفه،
because we make it our duty to find out
لأننا نجعل من واجبنا إيجاد
what's appropriate technology for Africa -- what's appropriately priced,
التكنلوجيا المناسبة لأفريقيا -- الأسعار المناسبة،
does the job, and we move on. Anesthesia machine:
ويقوم بالعمل، ونواصل المسير. آلة تخدير،
multi-parameter monitor, operating lights, suction.
شاشة مراقبة متعددة، إضاءة عمليات، شافطة.
This little unit here -- remember your little 12-volt plug in the car,
هذه الوحدة الصغيرة هنا-- تذكروا مقبس ال 12 فولت في سيارتكم،
that charges your, whatever, Game Boy, telephone?
الذي يقوم بشحن أي شئ -- لعبة طفل، هاتف؟
That's exactly how the outlets are designed.
هكذا بالضبط صُممت المنافذ.
Yes, it will take a solar panel. Yes a solar panel will charge it.
نعم، ستأخذ ألواح شمسية. نعم الشمس ستقوم بشحنها.
But if you've got mains as well, it will charge the batteries in there.
لكن إذا حصلت على أنابيب أيضاً، ستشحن بطارياتها هناك.
And guess what? We have a little pedal charger too, just in case.
وخمنوا ماذا؟ لدينا شواحن بدالات ايضاً، في حالة الحوجة.
And guess what, if it all fails,
وخمنوا ماذا، إذا فشلت،
if you can find a car that's still got a live battery
إذا أستطعت العثور على سيارة ببطارية تعمل
and you stick it in, it will still work. Then you can customize it.
يمكنك إيصالها لها، ويمكن أن تعمل. يمكنك تخصيصها.
Is it dental surgery you want? General surgery you want?
ما تحتاجه هل هي جراحة أسنان؟ جراحة عامة؟
Decide which instruments, stock it up with consumables.
قرر أي أجهزة، قم بتجميعها مع المستهلكات.
And currently we're working on oxygen -- oxygen delivery on-site.
ونعمل حالياً على الأوكسجين. إرسال الأوكسجين إلى الموقع.
The technology for oxygen delivery is not new.
تكنلوجيا إرسال الأوكسجين إلى الموقع ليست جديدة.
Oxygen concentrators are very old technology. What is new,
تراكيز الأوكسجين هي تكنلوجيا قديمة جداً. ما هو الجديد،
and what we will have in a few months, I hope,
وما سنحصل عليه خلال اشهر معدودة، كما أرجو،
is that ability to use this same renewable energy system
هو القدرة على إستخدام هذا النظام للطاقة المتجددة
to provide and produce oxygen on site. Zeolite -- it's not new --
لتقديم وإنتاج الأوكسجين في المكان. الزيوليت -- وهو ليس جديد --
zeolite removes nitrogen from air and nitrogen is 78 percent of air.
الزيوليت يزيل النيتروجين من الهواء والنيتروجين هو 78% من الهواء.
If you take nitrogen out, what's left? Oxygen, pretty much.
إذا أزلنا النيتروجين، ما الذي تبقى؟ الأوكسجين، ببساطة شديدة.
So that's not new. What we're doing is applying this technology to it.
إذاً ذلك جديد. ما نقوم به هو تطبيق هذه التكنلوجيا عليها.
These are the basic features of my device, or our device.
تلك هي الخصائص الأساسية لجهازي، أو جهازنا.
This is what makes it so special.
هذا ما يجعله مميزاً جداً.
Apart from the awards it's won,
بعيداً عن الجائزة التي حصل عليها،
it's portable and it's certified. It's registered, the MHRA --
إنه قابل للتنقل وحاصل على شهادة، وهو مسجل، MHRA --
and the CE mark, for those who don't know, for Europe, is the equivalent
و علامة ال CE ، لأؤلئك الذين لا يعلمون منكم، هي المكافئ الأوروبي
of the FDA in the U.S.
لل FDA في الولايات المتحدة.
If you compare it with what's on the market, price-wise,
إذا قمت بمقارنتها مع الموجود في السوق، بالنسبة للسعر،
size-wise, ease of use, complexity ...
الحجم، سهولة الإستخدام، والتعقيد.
This picture was taken last year.
هذه الصورة تم أخذها العام الماضي.
These are members of my graduating class, 1986.
هؤلاء هم زملائي في صف التخرج، عام 1986.
It was in this gentleman's house in the Potomac,
لقد كان في بيت هذا الشخص في بوتوماك،
for those of you who are familiar with Maryland.
لأؤلئك منكم الذين يعرفون ميريلاند.
There are too many of us outside and everybody,
هناك الكثير منا في الخارج والجميع،
just to borrow a bit from Hans -- Hans Rosling, he's my guy --
فقط لإستعارة القليل من هانس -- هانس روزلينغ، إنه بطلي--
if the size of the text represents what gets the most attention,
إذا كان حجم النص يمثل ما يحظى بمعظم الإنتباه،
it's the problems. But what we really need are African solutions
إنها المشاكل. لكن ما نحتاجه حقاً هو حلول أفريقية
that are appropriate for Africa -- looking at the culture,
مناسبة لافريقيا -- تراعي للثقافة،
looking at the people, looking at how much money they've got.
وتراعي للناس، تراعي لكم من المال لديهم.
African people, because they will do it with a passion, I hope.
الأفارقة، لأنهم يفعلونها بكل شغف، كما أرجو،
And lots and lots of that little bit down there, sacrifice.
والكثير والكثير من تلك، التضحية.
You have to do it. Africans have to do it,
يجب أن نفعلها. يجب على الأفارقة فعلها،
in conjunction with everyone else.
بالتزامن مع الجميع.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)